SystemVerilog Testbench Fundamentals Module 2
Learning objectives Master SystemVerilog testbench construction
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Master SystemVerilog testbench construction
Overview This module provides comprehensive coverage of SystemVerilog testbench construction. You'll learn how to build testbenches, generate clocks, handle resets, access signals, and create robust verification environments.
Syllabus topics
From MODULE2 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
Exercise scaffold The following command is shown on screen.
Practice & assessment
Exercises Clock Generation Reset Implementation Signal Access Timing Control Testbench Patterns
Assessment checklist Can generate clocks and manage clock domains Can implement reset patterns Can access and drive signals correctly Can use events and timing control Can apply common verification patterns Can structure testbenches effectively
Summary & next steps Master SystemVerilog testbench construction Complete module2/CHECKLIST.md Run ./scripts/module2.sh --check Next: Next module in course