Real-World Applications Module 7
Learning objectives Apply UVM to real-world verification scenarios
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Apply UVM to real-world verification scenarios
Overview This module applies UVM to real-world verification scenarios including DMA verification, protocol verification (UART, SPI, I2C), VIP development, and best practices. You'll learn how to verify complex designs, develop re
Syllabus topics
From MODULE7 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
module7/examples/dma/README.md
Hands-on: module7/examples/dma/
module7/examples/protocols/README.md
Hands-on: module7/examples/protocols/
module7/examples/vip/README.md
Hands-on: module7/examples/vip/
module7/examples/best_practices/README.md
Hands-on: module7/examples/best_practices/
Practice & assessment
From MODULE7 Learning Outcomes.
Exercises DMA Verification Protocol Verification VIP Development Best Practices System-Level Verification
Assessment checklist Can verify complex designs (DMA, protocols) Can develop reusable VIP Can apply best practices Can perform system-level verification Can create production-quality testbenches Understands protocol verification patterns
Summary & next steps Apply UVM to real-world verification scenarios Complete module7/CHECKLIST.md Review module7/EXAMPLES.md and run each lab Next: Next module in course