UVM Components Module 4
Learning objectives Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer
Overview This module covers the core UVM components used to build verification environments. You'll learn how to create agents, drivers, monitors, sequencers, and sequences to build complete verification environments. The module
Syllabus topics
From MODULE4 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
Exercise scaffold The following command is shown on screen.
Practice & assessment
Exercises Transaction Modeling Driver Implementation Monitor Implementation Sequencer and Sequences TLM Communication
Exercises Scoreboards Complete Agents
Assessment checklist Can design and implement transaction classes Can create drivers for DUT stimulus Can implement monitors for DUT observation Can build sequencers and sequences Can use TLM for component communication Can create scoreboards for result checking
Summary & next steps Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer Complete module4/CHECKLIST.md Run ./scripts/module4.sh --check Next: Next module in course