Welcome to module 4, UVM Components. In this module you will build complete uvm agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer.
Here is what you will learn in this module. Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer
Before you start, make sure you have these prerequisites. See module README
Learning path. Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer
Overview. This module covers the core UVM components used to build verification environments. You'll learn how to create agents, drivers...
Next section: Design architecture.
1. UVM agent internal architecture (1/3). Active agent: sequencer + driver + monitor (generates and observes stimulus) Passive agent: monitor only (observation/checking on monitored bus) Agent is_active config selects build-time component set Sequencer-driver TLM: driver.seq_item_port.connect(sequencer.seq_item_export) Refer to the diagram on the right.
1. UVM agent internal architecture (2/3). uvm_sequencer: Arbitrates sequences; exports seq_item_export uvm_driver: seq_item_port pulls items; drives virtual interface uvm_monitor: Passive observation; broadcasts via analysis port uvm_agent: Configures active/passive; builds child components
1. UVM agent internal architecture (3/3). uvm_sequence: Produces randomized/constrained transactions
2. Transaction-level data path (1/3). TLM ports: uvm_analysis_port / uvm_analysis_export for monitor → scoreboard Transactions implement do_copy, do_compare, convert2string for debug and checking Execution sequence: build agent → connect TLM → start sequence in run_phase 1: Sequence — randomize() transaction fields Refer to the diagram on the right.
2. Transaction-level data path (2/3). 2: Sequencer — Sends item to driver via TLM port 3: Driver — Drives interface signals from item 4: DUT — Responds on bus/interface 5: Monitor — Captures pin activity → transaction
2. Transaction-level data path (3/3). 6: Scoreboard — Compares expected vs observed (Module 4 examples)
3. Module 4 example progression (1/2). examples/transactions/ → data modeling fundamentals examples/drivers/, monitors/, sequencers/ → individual components examples/tlm/, scoreboards/ → communication and checking examples/agents/ → integrated active agent Refer to the diagram on the right.
3. Module 4 example progression (2/2). tests/uvm_tests/test_complete_agent_uvm.sv — full agent on interface DUT
RTL block diagram (reference). Module 4: DUT hierarchy and signal flow.
Verification / testbench diagram (reference). Module 4: stimulus, observation, and checking.
Next section: Execution & simulation flow.
How the example runs (toolchain). Match each bullet to files in the repository. Makefile: Verilator + UVM_HOME compile RTL, interface, and test_*.sv UVM phases: build → connect → run_test → report (same pattern as Module 2) Sequence → driver → DUT → monitor → scoreboard (read SCOREBOARD at end) Typical command: make SIM=verilator TEST=test_* (see module4 demo slide) Loopback / hooks connect...
Artifact flow (spec → sim) (1). Match each bullet to files in the repository. 1: Sequence — randomize() transaction fields 2: Sequencer — Sends item to driver via TLM port 3: Driver — Drives interface signals from item 4: DUT — Responds on bus/interface From MODULE4 — execution and artifact layout.
Artifact flow (spec → sim) (2). Match each bullet to files in the repository. 5: Monitor — Captures pin activity → transaction 6: Scoreboard — Compares expected vs observed (Module 4 examples) From MODULE4 — execution and artifact layout.
Example directory layout. Match each bullet to files in the repository. uvm_sequencer: Arbitrates sequences; exports seq_item_export uvm_driver: seq_item_port pulls items; drives virtual interface uvm_monitor: Passive observation; broadcasts via analysis port uvm_agent: Configures active/passive; builds child components uvm_sequence: Produces randomized/constrained transactions Match each path...
Follow these steps in order when working through this module. build agent connect TLM start sequence in run_phase Follow this order when tracing waveforms or debugging.
Next section: Verification & testing methods.
1. Component-level verification strategy. Verify each component in isolation before agent integration Driver: loopback or simple slave model confirms pin wiggles match items Monitor: drive known patterns; confirm reconstructed transactions Sequencer: run single sequence; count items completed vs requested Refer to the diagram on the right.
2. Agent integration and closure (1/2). Connect monitor analysis port to scoreboard export in connect_phase Use uvm_config_db to pass virtual interface to driver and monitor Regression: ./scripts/module4.sh --all-examples then --uvm-tests Pass criteria: scoreboard match count equals transaction count; no UVM_ERROR Refer to the diagram on the right.
2. Agent integration and closure (2/2). Waveform optional — rely on transaction logs and scoreboard summary first
Next section: Syllabus topics.
Next section: Protocol & design details.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.1: Transactions (module4/examples/transactions/transactions.sv) (1). BaseTransaction: Basic transaction with data and address fields ExtendedTransaction: Extended transaction with control and status fields ConstrainedTransaction: Transaction with randomization constraints Transaction Operations: Copy, comparison, and string conversion From MODULE4 Topics...
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.1: Transactions (module4/examples/transactions/transactions.sv) (2). Purpose: Provide human-readable string representation Usage: Debugging, logging, reporting Key: Override from uvm_object base class Purpose: Create independent copy of transaction From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.2: Drivers (module4/examples/drivers/drivers.sv) (1). SimpleDriver: Basic driver implementation with transaction reception ProtocolDriver: Protocol-aware driver with handshaking Driver-Sequencer Communication: Using seq_item_port for transaction flow Signal Driving: Converting transactions to DUT signals From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.2: Drivers (module4/examples/drivers/drivers.sv) (2). Purpose: Get transaction from sequencer (blocking) Usage: Called in driver's run_phase() forever loop Key: Blocks until sequencer provides transaction Purpose: Signal that transaction processing is complete From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.3: Monitors (module4/examples/monitors/monitors.sv) (1). SimpleMonitor: Basic monitor implementation with signal sampling ProtocolMonitor: Protocol-aware monitor with handshake monitoring Transaction Creation: Creating transactions from sampled signals Analysis Port: Forwarding transactions via analysis port From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.3: Monitors (module4/examples/monitors/monitors.sv) (2). Purpose: Broadcast transaction to all subscribers Usage: Called after creating transaction from sampled signals Key: Non-blocking, broadcasts to all connected subscribers Purpose: Create analysis port in constructor From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.4: Sequencers (module4/examples/sequencers/sequencers.sv) (1). SimpleSequence: Basic sequence implementation ExtendedSequence: Extended sequence with configurable item count Sequence Execution: Starting sequences on sequencers Sequence Item Generation: Creating and sending sequence items From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.4: Sequencers (module4/examples/sequencers/sequencers.sv) (2). Purpose: Generate and send sequence items Usage: Main sequence logic Key: Called when sequence is started Purpose: Request sequence item from sequencer From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.5: TLM (module4/examples/tlm/tlm.sv) (1). TlmProducer: Uses uvm_blocking_put_port to produce transactions TlmConsumer: Uses uvm_blocking_get_export to consume transactions AnalysisProducer: Uses uvm_analysis_port to broadcast transactions AnalysisSubscriber: Uses uvm_subscriber to receive transactions From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.5: TLM (module4/examples/tlm/tlm.sv) (2). Purpose: Send transaction to consumer (blocking) Usage: Producer sends transactions Key: Blocks until consumer receives Purpose: Receive transaction from producer (blocking) From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.6: Scoreboards (module4/examples/scoreboards/scoreboards.sv) (1). SimpleScoreboard: Basic scoreboard with transaction comparison Transaction Storage: Storing expected and actual transactions Comparison Logic: Comparing transactions for verification Result Reporting: Reporting pass/fail counts From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.6: Scoreboards (module4/examples/scoreboards/scoreboards.sv) (2). Purpose: Receive transactions from monitor Usage: Called automatically when monitor writes to analysis port Key: Compares actual vs expected results Purpose: Store expected transaction for later comparison From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.7: Complete Agents (module4/examples/agents/agents.sv) (1). CompleteAgent: Contains driver, monitor, and sequencer Agent Configuration: Configurable as active or passive Component Integration: Integrating all agent components Agent Testing: Testing complete agent functionality From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 4.7: Complete Agents (module4/examples/agents/agents.sv) (2). Purpose: Create agent components based on configuration Key: Active agent has driver+sequencer, passive has monitor only Monitor: Always created (both active and passive modes) Driver/Sequencer: Only created in active mode From MODULE4 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Verification flow (reference). Stimulus, DUT response, and check points for this module.
1. UVM Agent Architecture (1/9). Agent Overview and Structure Agent purpose and responsibilities Agent components (driver, monitor, sequencer) Agent configuration Active vs passive agents
1. UVM Agent Architecture (2/9). Driver for stimulus generation Monitor for observation Sequencer for sequence management Agent integration BaseTransaction: Basic transaction with data and address fields
1. UVM Agent Architecture (3/9). ConstrainedTransaction: Transaction with randomization constraints Transaction Operations: Copy, comparison, and string conversion Purpose: Provide human-readable string representation Usage: Debugging, logging, reporting Key: Override from uvm_object base class
1. UVM Agent Architecture (4/9). Usage: txn2.copy(txn1) - creates deep copy Key: Must call super.do_copy(rhs) first, then copy all fields Purpose: Compare two transactions for equality Usage: if (txn1.compare(txn2)) - returns 1 if equal Key: Returns 1 if all fields match, 0 otherwise
1. UVM Agent Architecture (5/9). Usage: txn.randomize() - returns 1 if successful Key: Constraints ensure protocol compliance Purpose: Post-process after randomization Usage: Calculate derived fields, validate constraints Key: Called automatically after randomize() succeeds
1. UVM Agent Architecture (6/9). Purpose: Type-safe conversion from uvm_object to specific type Usage: Required in do_copy() and do_compare() Key: Always check return value, handle type mismatch Purpose: Extend base transaction with additional fields Key: Must call super methods to handle base class fields
1. UVM Agent Architecture (7/9). Transaction fields and data members Transaction copy and comparison operations Extended transactions with inheritance Constrained random transactions convert2string() for debugging and logging
1. UVM Agent Architecture (8/9). do_compare() for transaction comparison randomize() for constrained random generation Constraints ensure protocol compliance Transaction creation and initialization Transaction copy operations
1. UVM Agent Architecture (9/9). Extended transaction inheritance Constrained random transaction generation
2. UVM Driver Implementation (1/8). Driver Purpose and Responsibilities Stimulus generation Protocol implementation Signal driving Transaction-to-signal conversion
2. UVM Driver Implementation (2/8). Driver class structure Sequencer communication Transaction reception Signal driving patterns SimpleDriver: Basic driver implementation with transaction reception
2. UVM Driver Implementation (3/8). Driver-Sequencer Communication: Using seq_item_port for transaction flow Signal Driving: Converting transactions to DUT signals Purpose: Get transaction from sequencer (blocking) Usage: Called in driver's run_phase() forever loop Key: Blocks until sequencer provides transaction
2. UVM Driver Implementation (4/8). Usage: Called after driving transaction to DUT Key: Allows sequencer to provide next transaction Purpose: Convert transaction to DUT signals Usage: Called after get_next_item() Key: Implements protocol-specific driving logic
2. UVM Driver Implementation (5/8). Key: Handles request/grant, timing, protocol compliance Purpose: Connect driver to sequencer Usage: In agent's connect_phase() Key: Establishes TLM communication channel Driver class structure extending uvm_driver
2. UVM Driver Implementation (6/8). Signal driving to DUT Driver-sequencer communication Protocol-specific driving patterns get_next_item() - Get transaction from sequencer (blocking) item_done() - Signal transaction completion
2. UVM Driver Implementation (7/8). TLM connection - seq_item_port.connect(sequencer.seq_item_export) Forever loop - Driver continuously processes transactions Driver creation and initialization Transaction reception from sequencer Signal driving to DUT
2. UVM Driver Implementation (8/8). Driver-sequencer communication
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (1/7). Monitor Purpose and Responsibilities DUT observation Signal sampling Transaction creation Analysis port usage
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (2/7). Monitor class structure Signal sampling Transaction creation Analysis port forwarding SimpleMonitor: Basic monitor implementation with signal sampling
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (3/7). Transaction Creation: Creating transactions from sampled signals Analysis Port: Forwarding transactions via analysis port Purpose: Broadcast transaction to all subscribers Usage: Called after creating transaction from sampled signals Key: Non-blocking, broadcasts to all connected subscribers
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (4/7). Key: Analysis ports created in constructor, not build_phase Purpose: Sample DUT signals and create transactions Key: Monitor is passive (doesn't drive DUT) Purpose: Connect monitor to subscribers (scoreboard, coverage, etc.) Key: One monitor can connect to multiple subscribers
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (5/7). Usage: Scoreboard, coverage collector, logger Key: Automatically called when monitor writes to analysis port Monitor class structure extending uvm_monitor Signal sampling from DUT Transaction creation from sampled signals
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (6/7). Protocol-specific monitoring ap.write(txn) - Broadcast transaction to subscribers Analysis port creation - In constructor, not build_phase Signal sampling - Wait for protocol events, sample signals Transaction creation - Create from sampled signals
3. UVM Monitor Implementation (7/7). Monitor creation and initialization Signal sampling from DUT Transaction creation from signals Analysis port forwarding Protocol-specific monitoring
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (1/8). Sequencer Implementation Sequencer purpose Sequence item management Sequence execution Sequencer-driver communication
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (2/8). Sequence items (uvm_sequence_item) Sequences (uvm_sequence) Sequence execution Sequence libraries SimpleSequence: Basic sequence implementation
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (3/8). Sequence Execution: Starting sequences on sequencers Sequence Item Generation: Creating and sending sequence items Purpose: Generate and send sequence items Usage: Main sequence logic Key: Called when sequence is started
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (4/8). Usage: Called before setting item fields Key: Blocking call, waits for sequencer availability Purpose: Send sequence item to driver Usage: Called after setting item fields Key: Item flows: Sequence → Sequencer → Driver
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (5/8). Usage: In test's run_phase() Key: Sequence executes body() task Purpose: Generate random test vectors Key: Constraints ensure valid values Purpose: Configurable sequence with parameters
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (6/8). Sequencer implementation Sequence items (uvm_sequence_item) Sequences (uvm_sequence) Sequence execution Sequence libraries
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (7/8). start_item(item) - Request item from sequencer finish_item(item) - Send item to driver seq.start(sequencer) - Start sequence execution Item flow: Sequence → Sequencer → Driver Sequencer creation and initialization
4. UVM Sequencer and Sequences (8/8). Sequence execution Sequencer-driver communication Sequence libraries
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (1/8). TLM Interfaces Put/get interfaces Peek interfaces Transport interfaces Analysis interfaces
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (2/8). TLM ports and exports TLM FIFOs Analysis ports and exports TLM connections TlmProducer: Uses uvm_blocking_put_port to produce transactions
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (3/8). AnalysisProducer: Uses uvm_analysis_port to broadcast transactions AnalysisSubscriber: Uses uvm_subscriber to receive transactions Purpose: Send transaction to consumer (blocking) Usage: Producer sends transactions Key: Blocks until consumer receives
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (4/8). Usage: Consumer receives transactions Key: Blocks until producer sends Purpose: Buffer between producer and consumer Usage: Decouples producer and consumer timing Key: FIFO stores transactions temporarily
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (5/8). Usage: One-to-many communication Key: Non-blocking, broadcasts to all subscribers Purpose: Receive transactions from analysis port Usage: Scoreboard, coverage, logger Key: Automatically called when producer writes
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (6/8). TLM ports and exports TLM FIFOs Analysis ports and exports TLM connections put_port.put(txn) - Send transaction (blocking)
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (7/8). ap.write(txn) - Broadcast transaction (non-blocking) write(t) - Receive in subscriber (automatic) TLM FIFO - Decouples producer and consumer Analysis port - One-to-many communication TLM port/export creation
5. TLM (Transaction-Level Modeling) (8/8). Transaction flow via TLM Analysis port broadcasting TLM FIFO usage
6. Scoreboards (1/8). Scoreboard Purpose Result checking Transaction comparison Pass/fail tracking Verification closure
6. Scoreboards (2/8). Scoreboard structure Transaction storage Comparison logic Result reporting SimpleScoreboard: Basic scoreboard with transaction comparison
6. Scoreboards (3/8). Comparison Logic: Comparing transactions for verification Result Reporting: Reporting pass/fail counts Purpose: Receive transactions from monitor Usage: Called automatically when monitor writes to analysis port Key: Compares actual vs expected results
6. Scoreboards (4/8). Usage: Called before actual transaction arrives Key: Queue stores expected transactions in order Purpose: Manage expected transaction queue Key: FIFO queue ensures order matching Purpose: Compare actual vs expected results
6. Scoreboards (5/8). Purpose: Report final test results Usage: Called in cleanup phase Key: Provides test pass/fail summary Purpose: Connect monitor to scoreboard Key: Monitor writes → Scoreboard receives
6. Scoreboards (6/8). Transaction comparison Result checking Pass/fail tracking write(txn) - Receive transaction from monitor add_expected(txn) - Store expected transaction
6. Scoreboards (7/8). Comparison logic - Compare actual vs expected Report phase - Final test results Analysis export - uvm_analysis_imp receives transactions Scoreboard creation and initialization Transaction storage
6. Scoreboards (8/8). Pass/fail tracking Result reporting
7. Complete Agent Example (1/6). Building Complete Agents Agent structure Component integration Agent configuration Active vs passive agents
7. Complete Agent Example (2/6). Agent Configuration: Configurable as active or passive Component Integration: Integrating all agent components Agent Testing: Testing complete agent functionality Purpose: Create agent components based on configuration Key: Active agent has driver+sequencer, passive has monitor only
7. Complete Agent Example (3/6). Driver/Sequencer: Only created in active mode Purpose: Connect agent components Key: Driver-sequencer connection only for active agents Note: Monitor analysis port connected in environment's connect_phase Purpose: Configure agent as active or passive
7. Complete Agent Example (4/6). Key: Active = driver+sequencer+monitor, Passive = monitor only Timing: Must be set in test's build_phase before agent creation Purpose: Use agent based on mode Key: Check is_active before using driver/sequencer Agent structure
7. Complete Agent Example (5/6). Agent configuration Active vs passive agents Active agent - Driver + Sequencer + Monitor Passive agent - Monitor only Configuration - Via ConfigDB before creation
7. Complete Agent Example (6/6). Connection - Driver-sequencer only for active agents Complete agent creation Component integration Agent configuration Active/passive agent modes
Run: Example 4.1: Transactions. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Run: Example 4.2: Drivers. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Run: Example 4.3: Monitors. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Run: Example 4.4: Sequencers. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Run: Example 4.5: TLM. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Run: Example 4.6: Scoreboards. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Run: Example 4.7: Complete Agents. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE4.md.
Next section: Hands-on examples.
Module 4 self-check. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Exercise scaffold. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository.
Example 1: Transactions. BaseTransaction: Basic transaction with data and address fields ExtendedTransaction: Extended transaction with control and status fields ConstrainedTransaction: Transaction with randomization constraints Transaction Operations: Copy, comparison, and string conversion module4/examples/transactions/README.md
Demo: Transactions. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 2: Drivers. SimpleDriver: Basic driver implementation with transaction reception ProtocolDriver: Protocol-aware driver with handshaking Driver-Sequencer Communication: Using seq_item_port for transaction flow Signal Driving: Converting transactions to DUT signals module4/examples/drivers/README.md
Demo: Drivers. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 3: Monitors. SimpleMonitor: Basic monitor implementation with signal sampling ProtocolMonitor: Protocol-aware monitor with handshake monitoring Transaction Creation: Creating transactions from sampled signals Analysis Port: Forwarding transactions via analysis port module4/examples/monitors/README.md
Demo: Monitors. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 4: Sequencers. SimpleSequence: Basic sequence implementation ExtendedSequence: Extended sequence with configurable item count Sequence Execution: Starting sequences on sequencers Sequence Item Generation: Creating and sending sequence items module4/examples/sequencers/README.md
Demo: Sequencers. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 5: TLM. TlmProducer: Uses uvm_blocking_put_port to produce transactions TlmConsumer: Uses uvm_blocking_get_export to consume transactions AnalysisProducer: Uses uvm_analysis_port to broadcast transactions AnalysisSubscriber: Uses uvm_subscriber to receive transactions module4/examples/tlm/README.md
Demo: TLM. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 6: Scoreboards. SimpleScoreboard: Basic scoreboard with transaction comparison Transaction Storage: Storing expected and actual transactions Comparison Logic: Comparing transactions for verification Result Reporting: Reporting pass/fail counts module4/examples/scoreboards/README.md
Demo: Scoreboards. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 7: Complete Agents. CompleteAgent: Contains driver, monitor, and sequencer Agent Configuration: Configurable as active or passive Component Integration: Integrating all agent components Agent Testing: Testing complete agent functionality module4/examples/agents/README.md
Demo: Complete Agents. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Next section: Practice & assessment.
By now you should be able to explain the following. Design and implement transaction classes Create drivers for DUT stimulus generation Implement monitors for DUT observation Build sequencers and sequences for test generation Use TLM for component communication From MODULE4 Learning Outcomes.
By now you should be able to explain the following. Build complete agents with all components integrated Apply UVM component patterns in testbenches From MODULE4 Learning Outcomes.
Exercises. Transaction Modeling Driver Implementation Monitor Implementation Sequencer and Sequences TLM Communication
Exercises. Scoreboards Complete Agents
Assessment checklist. Can design and implement transaction classes Can create drivers for DUT stimulus Can implement monitors for DUT observation Can build sequencers and sequences Can use TLM for component communication
In summary: Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer Next up: Next module in course. Build complete UVM agents with driver, monitor, and sequencer Complete module4/CHECKLIST.md Review module4/EXAMPLES.md and run each lab Next: Next module in course