Installation and Setup Module 0
Learning objectives Set up development environment and verify installation
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Set up development environment and verify installation
Overview This module covers the complete setup of your verification environment, including all required tools and dependencies. By the end of this module, you should have a working environment capable of running SystemVerilog UVM
Syllabus topics
From MODULE0 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
Hands-on: module0/examples/install/
Hands-on: module0/examples/project/
Hands-on: module0/examples/install-full/
Hands-on: module0/examples/hello/
Practice & assessment
From MODULE0 Learning Outcomes.
Exercises Installation Verification Environment Setup First Test IDE Configuration Project Structure
Assessment checklist Can install all required tools independently Can set up Verilator Can verify Verilator installation Can verify UVM library installation Can configure IDE for verification work Can create and run a simple test
Summary & next steps Set up development environment and verify installation Complete module0/CHECKLIST.md Review module0/EXAMPLES.md and run each lab Next: Next module in course