UVM Miscellaneous Utilities Module 8
Learning objectives Master UVM utility classes
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Master UVM utility classes
Overview This module covers UVM utility classes including Command Line Processor, comparators, recorders, pools, queues, and string/math/random utilities. These utilities provide essential functionality for building robust and fl
Syllabus topics
From MODULE8 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
Practice & assessment
Exercises Command Line Processor Comparators Recorders Pools Queues
Exercises String Utilities Math Utilities Random Utilities Integration
Assessment checklist Can use UVM utility classes effectively Can parse command-line arguments using CLP Can compare transactions using comparators Can record and playback transactions Can use pools and queues for memory management Can apply string, math, and random utilities
Summary & next steps Master UVM utility classes Complete module8/CHECKLIST.md Run ./scripts/module8.sh --check Next: Next module in course