SystemVerilog and Verification Basics Module 1
Learning objectives Understand SystemVerilog for verification and verification fundamentals
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Understand SystemVerilog for verification and verification fundamentals
Overview This module establishes the foundation for verification work. You'll learn essential SystemVerilog concepts used in verification and understand the fundamental principles of hardware verification.
Syllabus topics
From MODULE1 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
Exercise scaffold The following command is shown on screen.
Practice & assessment
Exercises Transaction Class Design Interface Design Package Organization Data Structure Usage Error Handling
Assessment checklist Can create SystemVerilog classes with inheritance Can design and use interfaces with modports Can organize code using packages Can use appropriate data structures Can implement error handling and logging Can write basic SystemVerilog testbenches
Summary & next steps Understand SystemVerilog for verification and verification fundamentals Complete module1/CHECKLIST.md Run ./scripts/module1.sh --check Next: Next module in course