Complex Testbenches Module 6
Learning objectives Build production-quality multi-agent testbenches
Prerequisites See module README
Learning path Build production-quality multi-agent testbenches
Overview This module covers building complex, production-quality testbenches with multiple agents, protocol verification, and system-level architecture. You'll learn how to coordinate multiple agents, verify protocols, implement
Syllabus topics
From MODULE6 Topics Covered.
Hands-on examples
Run from course repository root.
Exercise scaffold The following command is shown on screen.
Practice & assessment
Exercises Testbench Architecture Multi-Agent Coordination Protocol Verification Protocol Checkers Multi-Channel Scoreboards
Assessment checklist Can design complex testbench architectures Can coordinate multiple agents Can verify protocols Can implement protocol checkers Can build multi-channel scoreboards Can apply production-quality testbench patterns
Summary & next steps Build production-quality multi-agent testbenches Complete module6/CHECKLIST.md Run ./scripts/module6.sh --check Next: Next module in course