Welcome to module 0, Installation and Setup. In this module you will set up development environment and verify installation.
Here is what you will learn in this module. Set up development environment and verify installation
Before you start, make sure you have these prerequisites. See module README
Learning path. Set up development environment and verify installation
Overview. This module covers the complete setup of your verification environment, including all required tools and dependencies. By the end of...
Next section: Design architecture.
1. Course repository layout (1/3). Project-local install (--local) keeps tools inside the repo for reproducibility WSL2/Linux is the primary target; macOS supported via Homebrew Environment variables: VERILATOR_ROOT, UVM_HOME must resolve before running labs tools/verilator/: Git submodule — SystemVerilog/Verilog simulator (build from source) Refer to the diagram on the right.
1. Course repository layout (2/3). tools/uvm-2017/: IEEE 1800.2-2017 UVM library sources (UVM_HOME) scripts/installation.sh: One-shot installer for Verilator + UVM + dependencies scripts/moduleN.sh: Per-module example orchestrator (modules 1–8) moduleN/examples/: Hands-on labs referenced by slides and EXAMPLES.md
1. Course repository layout (3/3). media/moduleN/: Generated slides, PDF, and narrated video per module
2. Build and simulation artifact flow (1/2). Verilator compiles design + testbench into a single fast C++ binary UVM examples add -I$UVM_HOME/src and +define+UVM_NO_DPI for Verilator compatibility Self-check flow: install → verilator --version → ./scripts/module0.sh --check → run Module 1 lab 1: Source .v/.sv — RTL and testbench SystemVerilog Refer to the diagram on the right.
2. Build and simulation artifact flow (2/2). Match each bullet to files in the repository. 2: verilator --cc — Emits C++ model under obj_dir/ 3: make -C obj_dir — Links Vtop (or V) executable 4: ./obj_dir/V* — Runs simulation; prints PASS/FAIL or UVM report 5: *.vcd (optional) — Waveform when --trace enabled
Next section: Installation & execution.
How to run this module. From repo root: ./scripts/module0.sh --check — validate environment ./scripts/module0.sh --demo — print demo commands to run locally ./scripts/module0.sh --scaffold — create ~/unix_practice/ exercise files Open module0/EXAMPLES.md — run each numbered lab in your terminal Track progress with module0/CHECKLIST.md before moving on From MODULE0 — execution and artifact layout.
Artifact flow (spec → sim) (1). Match each bullet to files in the repository. 1: Source .v/.sv — RTL and testbench SystemVerilog 2: verilator --cc — Emits C++ model under obj_dir/ 3: make -C obj_dir — Links Vtop (or V) executable 4: ./obj_dir/V* — Runs simulation; prints PASS/FAIL or UVM report From MODULE0 — execution and artifact layout.
Artifact flow (spec → sim) (2). Match each bullet to files in the repository. 5: *.vcd (optional) — Waveform when --trace enabled From MODULE0 — execution and artifact layout.
Example directory layout (1). Match each bullet to files in the repository. tools/verilator/: Git submodule — SystemVerilog/Verilog simulator (build from source) tools/uvm-2017/: IEEE 1800.2-2017 UVM library sources (UVM_HOME) scripts/installation.sh: One-shot installer for Verilator + UVM + dependencies scripts/moduleN.sh: Per-module example orchestrator (modules 1–8) moduleN/examples/...
Example directory layout (2). Match each bullet to files in the repository. media/moduleN/: Generated slides, PDF, and narrated video per module Match each path to files under module/examples/.
Follow these steps in order when working through this module. install verilator --version ./scripts/module0.sh --check run Module 1 lab
Next section: Verification & testing methods.
1. Environment verification strategy (1/2). Run ./scripts/installation.sh (or per-tool scripts) before any module labs Verify compiler toolchain: gcc --version, make --version, git --version Confirm Verilator: verilator --version and a minimal --lint-only compile Confirm UVM: echo $UVM_HOME points at tools/uvm-2017/1800.2-2017-1.0/src Refer to the diagram on the right.
1. Environment verification strategy (2/2). Use ./scripts/module0.sh --check for an automated PASS summary
2. Smoke test and troubleshooting workflow (1/2). Smoke test: compile one trivial Verilog file with Verilator; expect clean exit UVM smoke: run module3/examples/class_hierarchy after Module 0 completes Common failures: missing UVM_HOME, wrong Verilator version, WSL path issues Logs: capture terminal output; search for Error, %Error, UVM_FATAL Refer to the diagram on the right.
2. Smoke test and troubleshooting workflow (2/2). Escalation: re-run installer with --from-submodule for a clean Verilator build
Next section: Syllabus topics.
Before you start, make sure you have these prerequisites. Operating System Support Linux (Ubuntu/Debian, CentOS/RHEL, Fedora) macOS (Intel and Apple Silicon) Windows (WSL2 recommended) Hardware Requirements
Before you start, make sure you have these prerequisites. 10GB free disk space Multi-core processor recommended Software Prerequisites C/C++ compiler (GCC 7+, Clang 10+, or MSVC) Make or Ninja build system
Before you start, make sure you have these prerequisites. Perl (for UVM library)
2. Verilator Installation (1/6). What is Verilator? Open-source Verilog/SystemVerilog simulator Fast compilation and simulation Limited SystemVerilog support (see limitations section) Automated Installation (Recommended)
2. Verilator Installation (2/6). The script automatically: Checks for existing installations Installs system dependencies (build tools, libraries) Sets up git submodule in tools/verilator/ Builds and installs Verilator
2. Verilator Installation (3/6). Manual Installation Methods Linux Installation Ubuntu/Debian: sudo apt-get install verilator CentOS/RHEL: sudo yum install verilator or sudo dnf install verilator Fedora: sudo dnf install verilator
2. Verilator Installation (4/6). macOS Installation Homebrew installation: brew install verilator MacPorts installation (alternative) Building from source Windows/WSL2 Installation
2. Verilator Installation (5/6). Building from source in WSL2 Verifying installation Uninstallation Verification Steps Check Verilator version: verilator --version
2. Verilator Installation (6/6). Verify compilation works
3. UVM Library Installation (1/5). What is UVM? Universal Verification Methodology IEEE 1800.2-2017 standard Industry-standard verification framework Automated Installation (Recommended)
3. UVM Library Installation (2/5). The script automatically: Downloads Accellera UVM 2017-1.0 tarball to tools/uvm-2017/ Extracts and sets up UVM library Creates environment setup script (scripts/setup_uvm_env.sh) Configures UVM library paths
3. UVM Library Installation (3/5). From Accellera Tarball: From System Package (if available): Some Linux distributions provide UVM packages Check your distribution's package manager Uninstallation
3. UVM Library Installation (4/5). UVM_HOME: Path to UVM library UVM_VERBOSITY: Default verbosity level Include paths for compilation Verification Steps Check UVM library exists: ls $UVM_HOME/uvm_pkg.sv (after sourcing scripts/setup_uvm_env.sh)
3. UVM Library Installation (5/5). Verify UVM classes available
4. Commercial Simulator Setup (Optional) (1/2). Synopsys VCS Installation from Synopsys License setup UVM library integration Mentor QuestaSim/ModelSim
4. Commercial Simulator Setup (Optional) (2/2). License setup UVM library integration Cadence Xcelium Installation from Cadence License setup
5. Build System Configuration (1/3). Makefile Setup Basic Makefile for Verilator Compilation flags Include paths Test execution
5. Build System Configuration (2/3). SystemVerilog flags: -sv, --timing Include paths: +incdir+$UVM_HOME (UVM_HOME already points to the src directory) Optimization flags Coverage options Commercial Simulator Setup
5. Build System Configuration (3/3). Simulation scripts Waveform generation
6. IDE Setup and Configuration (1/3). Recommended IDEs VS Code with SystemVerilog extension Verible (SystemVerilog linter/formatter) Sigasi Studio (commercial) Vim/Neovim with LSP
6. IDE Setup and Configuration (2/3). SystemVerilog extension setup Verilator integration Debugging configuration Task runner setup for simulations Extension recommendations
6. IDE Setup and Configuration (3/3). SystemVerilog formatting (Verible) Linting (Verilator, Verible) Code formatting on save Syntax highlighting
7. Project Structure Setup (1/4). Directory Structure Source code organization Test directory structure DUT (Design Under Test) organization Configuration files
7. Project Structure Setup (2/4). Git Submodules Management Verilator is managed as a git submodule in tools/verilator/ UVM is downloaded as a tarball to tools/uvm-2017/ (not a git submodule) Initialize submodules: ./scripts/init_submodules.sh or git submodule update --init --recursive Update submodules: ./scripts/update_submodules.sh or git submodule update --remote
7. Project Structure Setup (3/4). Remove submodule: ./scripts/remove_submodule.sh  Makefile/Configuration Simple Makefile for running tests Verilator configuration Environment variable management
7. Project Structure Setup (4/4). Git initialization .gitignore for SystemVerilog and simulation (include build artifacts, waveforms) Initial commit structure Git submodules in .gitmodules file (only Verilator, not UVM)
8. First "Hello World" Verification Test (1/3). Prerequisites Ensure all tools are installed: ./scripts/installation.sh Verify tools are accessible: verilator --version and ls $UVM_HOME/uvm_pkg.sv (after sourcing scripts/setup_uvm_env.sh) Simple DUT Creation Basic Verilog module (e.g., AND gate)
8. First "Hello World" Verification Test (2/3). SystemVerilog Test Basic SystemVerilog testbench structure Clock generation Signal driving and reading Running the test
8. First "Hello World" Verification Test (3/3). First UVM test class Basic UVM phases Running UVM test Understanding output
9. Verilator Limitations and Workarounds (1/3). Known Limitations Limited SystemVerilog support Some UVM classes may not work Complex TLM connections may fail Full assertion support limited
9. Verilator Limitations and Workarounds (2/3). Use simplified patterns where possible Document commercial alternatives Focus on concepts over tool features Commercial Simulator Alternatives When Verilator doesn't support a feature
9. Verilator Limitations and Workarounds (3/3). Compatibility notes
10. Troubleshooting Common Issues (1/4). Verilator Issues Compilation errors Missing dependencies Version compatibility Path issues
10. Troubleshooting Common Issues (2/4). UVM Library Issues Import errors Path configuration Version compatibility Compilation errors
10. Troubleshooting Common Issues (3/4). Makefile errors Include path problems Compilation flags IDE Issues SystemVerilog syntax highlighting
10. Troubleshooting Common Issues (4/4). Debugging not working
11. Verification Checklist (1/3). C/C++ compiler installed and working Verilator installed and verified Using script: ./scripts/install_verilator.sh --from-submodule Verify: verilator --version UVM library installed and verified
11. Verification Checklist (2/3). Verify: ls $UVM_HOME/uvm_pkg.sv (after sourcing scripts/setup_uvm_env.sh) All tools verified together: Run ./scripts/installation.sh and verify with verilator --version and ls $UVM_HOME/uvm_pkg.sv (after... IDE configured and working First test runs successfully Can create and run simple testbench
11. Verification Checklist (3/3). Know how to get help when stuck Understand Verilator limitations
Next section: Hands-on examples.
Module 0 self-check. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Demo: Verify toolchain. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Demo: Project layout. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Demo: Optional full install. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Demo: First smoke test. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Next section: Practice & assessment.
By now you should be able to explain the following. Install and configure all required tools Set up Verilator Install and verify UVM library Configure your IDE for verification work Create a basic project structure From MODULE0 Learning Outcomes.
By now you should be able to explain the following. Understand Verilator limitations Troubleshoot common installation issues From MODULE0 Learning Outcomes.
Exercises. Installation Verification Environment Setup First Test IDE Configuration Project Structure
Assessment checklist. Can install all required tools independently Can set up Verilator Can verify Verilator installation Can verify UVM library installation Can configure IDE for verification work
In summary: Set up development environment and verify installation Next up: Next module in course. Set up development environment and verify installation Complete module0/CHECKLIST.md Review module0/EXAMPLES.md and run each lab Next: Next module in course