Welcome to module 3, UVM Basics. In this module you will master uvm class hierarchy and phases.
Here is what you will learn in this module. Master UVM class hierarchy and phases
Before you start, make sure you have these prerequisites. See module README
Learning path. Master UVM class hierarchy and phases
Overview. This module introduces the Universal Verification Methodology (UVM) using SystemVerilog. You'll learn the fundamental UVM concepts...
Next section: Design architecture.
1. UVM class hierarchy (1/3). Object hierarchy: uvm_object → uvm_sequence_item → your transaction Component hierarchy: uvm_component → driver/monitor/agent/env/test Factory macros (uvm_component_utils) register types for type_id::create() Component tree: Test → Env → Agent →  Refer to the diagram on the right.
1. UVM class hierarchy (2/3). uvm_test: Top-level; calls run_test(), owns environment uvm_env: Contains agents, scoreboard, coverage (as needed) uvm_agent: Groups driver, monitor, sequencer on one interface uvm_driver: Converts sequence items to pin wiggles
1. UVM class hierarchy (3/3). uvm_monitor: Observes bus/DUT; emits transactions uvm_sequence_item: Transaction payload (data, address, etc.)
2. UVM phase graph and execution order (1/2). Build-time (top-down): build_phase → connect_phase → end_of_elaboration_phase Run-time (bottom-up): run_phase with objections controlling sim time Report: report_phase summarizes UVM_INFO/WARNING/ERROR counts super.build_phase(phase) required in every override to preserve hierarchy Refer to the diagram on the right.
This section covers installation, setup, and how to run the examples. Simulation flow: elaboration → run_test() → phases → $finish
3. Module 3 repository map. 1: module3/examples/class_hierarchy/ — Minimal full UVM hierarchy demo 2: module3/examples/phases/ — Phase callback visibility 3: module3/dut/simple_blocks/adder.v — Small RTL for integrated UVM test 4: module3/tests/uvm_tests/test_adder_uvm.sv — End-to-end UVM testbench Refer to the diagram on the right.
RTL block diagram (reference). Module 3: DUT hierarchy and signal flow.
Verification / testbench diagram (reference). Module 3: stimulus, observation, and checking.
Next section: Execution & simulation flow.
How the example runs (toolchain). Match each bullet to files in the repository. Makefile: Verilator + UVM_HOME compile RTL, interface, and test_*.sv UVM phases: build → connect → run_test → report (same pattern as Module 2) Sequence → driver → DUT → monitor → scoreboard (read SCOREBOARD at end) Typical command: make SIM=verilator TEST=test_* (see module3 demo slide) Loopback / hooks connect...
Artifact flow (spec → sim). Match each bullet to files in the repository. 1: module3/examples/class_hierarchy/ — Minimal full UVM hierarchy demo 2: module3/examples/phases/ — Phase callback visibility 3: module3/dut/simple_blocks/adder.v — Small RTL for integrated UVM test 4: module3/tests/uvm_tests/test_adder_uvm.sv — End-to-end UVM testbench From MODULE3 — execution and artifact layout.
Example directory layout (1). Match each bullet to files in the repository. uvm_test: Top-level; calls run_test(), owns environment uvm_env: Contains agents, scoreboard, coverage (as needed) uvm_agent: Groups driver, monitor, sequencer on one interface uvm_driver: Converts sequence items to pin wiggles uvm_monitor: Observes bus/DUT; emits transactions Match each path to files under...
Example directory layout (2). Match each bullet to files in the repository. uvm_sequence_item: Transaction payload (data, address, etc.) Match each path to files under module/examples/.
Follow these steps in order when working through this module. ./scripts/module3.sh --class-hierarchy UVM report PASS elaboration run_test() Follow this order when tracing waveforms or debugging.
Follow these steps in order when working through this module. phases $finish Follow this order when tracing waveforms or debugging.
Next section: Verification & testing methods.
1. UVM infrastructure patterns. Factory — create components with type_id::create(); enable overrides later ConfigDB — pass virtual interfaces and config objects down the hierarchy Reporting — uvm_info/uvm_error with verbosity and ID filtering Objections — raise_objection/drop_objection in run_phase hold simulation alive Refer to the diagram on the right.
2. Verilator + UVM execution strategy (1/2). Compile with -I$UVM_HOME/src +define+UVM_NO_DPI (no DPI for Verilator) C++ main calls uvm_main or wrapper that invokes run_test("MyTest") Start with standalone examples (no DUT) to learn hierarchy and phases Progress to test_adder_uvm — connect virtual interface to RTL adder Refer to the diagram on the right.
This section covers installation, setup, and how to run the examples. Closure: zero UVM_ERROR/UVM_FATAL; expected INFO lines in log
Next section: Syllabus topics.
Next section: Protocol & design details.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.1: Class Hierarchy (module3/examples/class_hierarchy/class_hierarchy.sv) (1). Transaction Class (MyTransaction): Extends uvm_sequence_item (uvm_object hierarchy) Driver Class (MyDriver): Extends uvm_driver (uvm_component hierarchy) Monitor Class (MyMonitor): Extends uvm_monitor (uvm_component hierarchy) Agent Class (MyAgent): Extends uvm_agent...
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.1: Class Hierarchy (module3/examples/class_hierarchy/class_hierarchy.sv) (2). Environment Class (MyEnv): Extends uvm_env, top-level verification environment Test Class (ClassHierarchyTest): Extends uvm_test, orchestrates test execution Purpose: Automatically register class with UVM factory Usage: Must be inside class definition From MODULE3 Topics Covered...
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.2: Phases (module3/examples/phases/phases.sv) (1). Build-Time Phases: Top-down execution (parent before child) Run-Time Phases: Bottom-up execution (child before parent) Cleanup Phases: Bottom-up execution (child before parent) Phase Execution Order: Demonstrates all UVM phases From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.2: Phases (module3/examples/phases/phases.sv) (2). Purpose: Component construction and setup Execution: Top-down (parent before child) Key: Use super.build_phase(phase) to maintain hierarchy Purpose: Test execution phases From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.3: Reporting (module3/examples/reporting/reporting.sv) (1). Severity Levels: INFO, WARNING, ERROR, FATAL Verbosity Levels: UVM_LOW, UVM_MEDIUM, UVM_HIGH, UVM_FULL, UVM_DEBUG Message Formatting: Formatted messages with data values Hierarchical Reporting: Component context in messages From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.3: Reporting (module3/examples/reporting/reporting.sv) (2). Purpose: Print formatted messages with severity Parameters: TAG: Message category/tag Message: Text to display From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.4: ConfigDB (module3/examples/configdb/configdb.sv) (1). Setting Configuration: Global and component-specific Getting Configuration: Hierarchical lookup Configuration Objects: Complex configuration data Scalar Values: Simple configuration values From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.4: ConfigDB (module3/examples/configdb/configdb.sv) (2). Purpose: Store configuration in database Syntax: uvm_config_db#(type)::set(contxt, path, field, value) Parameters: contxt: Context (usually this in test) From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.5: Factory (module3/examples/factory/factory.sv) (1). Factory Registration: Automatic registration via uvm_object_utils Factory Creation: Using type_id::create() Type Override: Substituting base class with extended class Instance Override: Overriding specific instances From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.5: Factory (module3/examples/factory/factory.sv) (2). Purpose: Automatically register class with factory Usage: Must be inside class definition Key: Enables factory-based creation and overrides Purpose: Create objects/components via factory From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.6: Objections (module3/examples/objections/objections.sv) (1). Raising Objections: Keep simulation running Dropping Objections: Allow phase completion Multiple Objections: Per-component objection tracking Coordinated Completion: Phase completes when all objections dropped From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Example 3.6: Objections (module3/examples/objections/objections.sv) (2). Purpose: Keep phase running until objection is dropped Usage: Call at start of run_phase() or other run-time phases Parameters: this: Component raising objection From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: UVM Factory Macros and Methods (1). Purpose: Register class with UVM factory Location: Inside class definition Enables: Factory creation and overrides Syntax: ClassName::type_id::create(name, parent) From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: UVM Factory Macros and Methods (2). Returns: Handle to created object/component Key: Factory applies overrides automatically From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: UVM Reporting Macros (1). UVM_LOW - Always displayed (default) UVM_MEDIUM - Medium detail (most common) UVM_HIGH - High detail UVM_FULL - Full detail From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: UVM Reporting Macros (2). UVM_DEBUG - Debug-level detail From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: ConfigDB Methods (1). Set configuration in test's build_phase() before creating components Get configuration in component's build_phase() Always check return value of get() Provide default values if configuration not found From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: ConfigDB Methods (2). Use hierarchical paths for component-specific configuration From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Objection Methods. Must raise objection if doing work in run-time phase Must drop objection when work completes Phase completes when all objections are dropped Each raise_objection() must have matching drop_objection() From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Component Utility Methods. Purpose: Component identification Usage: Logging, debugging, hierarchical paths From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Sequence Methods (1). Purpose: Generate and send transactions to driver Usage: Sequences generate test vectors Flow: Sequence → Sequencer → Driver → DUT Purpose: Post-processing after randomization From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Sequence Methods (2). Usage: Calculate expected results, validate data From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: TLM Port Methods (Driver) (1). Purpose: Driver-sequencer communication Methods: get_next_item(txn): Get next transaction (blocking) item_done(): Signal transaction processing complete From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: TLM Port Methods (Driver) (2). Flow: Sequencer provides → Driver receives → DUT From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Analysis Port Methods (Monitor/Scoreboard) (1). Purpose: Broadcast transactions to subscribers Usage: Monitor sends transactions to scoreboard, coverage, etc. Purpose: Receive transactions from monitor Usage: Scoreboard checks DUT behavior From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Analysis Port Methods (Monitor/Scoreboard) (2). Purpose: Connect analysis port to analysis export Usage: Establish monitor → scoreboard communication From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Virtual Interface Methods. Purpose: Get virtual interface handle Usage: Driver/monitor access DUT signals via virtual interface Setting: uvm_config_db#(virtual interface_type)::set(null, "*", "vif", vif_inst) From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Protocol and design detail: Top-Level UVM Functions. Purpose: Start UVM test execution Parameters: Test class name (string) Behavior: Creates test instance, executes all phases Override: +UVM_TESTNAME=TestName command line option From MODULE3 Topics Covered — protocol/design depth.
Verification flow (reference). Stimulus, DUT response, and check points for this module.
1. Introduction to UVM (1/8). Universal Verification Methodology UVM standard (IEEE 1800.2-2017) UVM class library Methodology benefits Industry adoption
1. Introduction to UVM (2/8). Reusability Standardization Scalability Maintainability Transaction Class (MyTransaction): Extends uvm_sequence_item (uvm_object hierarchy)
1. Introduction to UVM (3/8). Monitor Class (MyMonitor): Extends uvm_monitor (uvm_component hierarchy) Agent Class (MyAgent): Extends uvm_agent, demonstrates component composition Environment Class (MyEnv): Extends uvm_env, top-level verification environment Test Class (ClassHierarchyTest): Extends uvm_test, orchestrates test execution Purpose: Automatically register class with UVM factory
1. Introduction to UVM (4/8). Key: Enables factory-based object creation Purpose: Initialize UVM objects and components Parameters: name: Component/object name parent: Parent component (for hierarchy)
1. Introduction to UVM (5/8). Purpose: Implement UVM phase behavior Key: Must call super.build_phase(phase) etc. to maintain hierarchy Objections: Use in run_phase() to control simulation Purpose: Create objects/components using factory Syntax: ClassName::type_id::create(name, parent)
1. Introduction to UVM (6/8). Purpose: Connect component ports in connect_phase() Usage: Connect driver to sequencer, monitor to scoreboard, etc. Purpose: Provide human-readable string representation Usage: Debugging, logging, reporting uvm_object - Base class for all UVM objects (transactions, sequences)
1. Introduction to UVM (7/8). Component hierarchy: Test → Environment → Agent → Driver/Monitor Component creation using factory pattern Factory macros (uvm_object_utils, uvm_component_utils) enable registration Phase functions/tasks implement component behavior Factory creation (type_id::create()) enables overrides
1. Introduction to UVM (8/8). Phase execution demonstration Component creation and connection UVM report summary
2. UVM Class Hierarchy (1/3). Object vs Component uvm_object - Base for transactions, sequences uvm_component - Base for testbench components Lifetime differences Hierarchy differences
2. UVM Class Hierarchy (2/3). uvm_test - Top-level test class uvm_env - Verification environment uvm_agent - Agent containing driver, monitor, sequencer uvm_driver - Drives transactions to DUT uvm_monitor - Observes DUT behavior
2. UVM Class Hierarchy (3/3). Object Classes uvm_sequence_item - Base transaction class uvm_sequence - Sequence of transactions Class relationships and inheritance
3. UVM Phases (1/8). Build-Time Phases (Top-down) build_phase() - Component construction connect_phase() - Component connections end_of_elaboration_phase() - Final setup start_of_simulation_phase() - Simulation start
3. UVM Phases (2/8). pre_reset_phase(), reset_phase(), post_reset_phase() pre_configure_phase(), configure_phase(), post_configure_phase() pre_main_phase(), main_phase(), post_main_phase() pre_shutdown_phase(), shutdown_phase(), post_shutdown_phase() Cleanup Phases (Bottom-up)
3. UVM Phases (3/8). check_phase() - Final checks report_phase() - Generate reports final_phase() - Final cleanup Build-Time Phases: Top-down execution (parent before child) Run-Time Phases: Bottom-up execution (child before parent)
3. UVM Phases (4/8). Phase Execution Order: Demonstrates all UVM phases Purpose: Component construction and setup Execution: Top-down (parent before child) Key: Use super.build_phase(phase) to maintain hierarchy Purpose: Test execution phases
3. UVM Phases (5/8). Key: Use objections in main_phase() to control simulation Purpose: Result extraction and reporting Execution: Bottom-up (child before parent) Key: Use for final verification and reporting Purpose: Get component identification
3. UVM Phases (6/8). Build-time phases execute top-down (parent before child) Run-time phases execute bottom-up (child before parent) Cleanup phases execute bottom-up (child before parent) Phases enable structured testbench execution Build-time phases are functions (no delays allowed)
3. UVM Phases (7/8). Cleanup phases are functions (no delays allowed) Must call super.phase_name(phase) to maintain hierarchy Use get_name() and get_full_name() for component identification All build-time phases executed in order All run-time phases executed in order
3. UVM Phases (8/8). Phase execution logging
4. UVM Reporting (1/8). UVM Messaging System Severity levels: FATAL, ERROR, WARNING, INFO, DEBUG Verbosity levels: UVM_LOW, UVM_MEDIUM, UVM_HIGH, UVM_FULL, UVM_DEBUG Message formatting Hierarchical reporting
4. UVM Reporting (2/8). Verbosity Levels: UVM_LOW, UVM_MEDIUM, UVM_HIGH, UVM_FULL, UVM_DEBUG Message Formatting: Formatted messages with data values Hierarchical Reporting: Component context in messages Purpose: Print formatted messages with severity Parameters:
4. UVM Reporting (3/8). Message: Text to display Verbosity: For uvm_info only (UVM_LOW, UVM_MEDIUM, etc.) Usage: Standard UVM messaging Purpose: Include data values in messages Uses: $sformatf() for string formatting
4. UVM Reporting (4/8). Purpose: Control message visibility Usage: Set in build_phase() or test Levels: UVM_LOW < UVM_MEDIUM < UVM_HIGH < UVM_FULL < UVM_DEBUG Purpose: Include component hierarchy in messages Uses: get_full_name() for hierarchical path
4. UVM Reporting (5/8). WARNING: Potential issues (non-fatal) ERROR: Actual errors (may stop simulation) FATAL: Fatal errors (stops simulation immediately) UVM_LOW: Always displayed (default) UVM_MEDIUM: Medium detail (default for most messages)
4. UVM Reporting (6/8). UVM_FULL: Full detail UVM_DEBUG: Debug-level detail Severity indicates message importance Verbosity controls message visibility Messages include component hierarchy context
4. UVM Reporting (7/8). uvm_info is most common (with verbosity control) uvm_warning for non-critical issues uvm_error for errors (may stop simulation) uvm_fatal for fatal errors (stops simulation) Use $sformatf() for formatted messages with data
4. UVM Reporting (8/8). Verbosity control demonstrated Formatted messages with data Hierarchical message context
5. ConfigDB (1/7). Configuration Database Basics Setting configuration Getting configuration Configuration hierarchy Configuration objects
5. ConfigDB (2/7). Getting Configuration: Hierarchical lookup Configuration Objects: Complex configuration data Scalar Values: Simple configuration values Purpose: Store configuration in database Syntax: uvm_config_db#(type)::set(contxt, path, field, value)
5. ConfigDB (3/7). contxt: Context (usually this in test) path: Component path ("*" for global, "comp_name" for specific) field: Configuration field name (string) value: Value to store Usage: Set in test's build_phase() before creating components
5. ConfigDB (4/7). Syntax: uvm_config_db#(type)::get(contxt, path, field, var) Returns: 1 if found, 0 if not found Usage: Get in component's build_phase() Key: Always check return value, provide defaults if not found Purpose: String representation of configuration
5. ConfigDB (5/7). ConfigDB enables flexible test configuration Configuration can be set globally or per-component Components look up configuration in build_phase() Hierarchical paths enable component-specific config Set before create: Configuration must be set before components are created
5. ConfigDB (6/7). Check return value: Always check if get() succeeded Provide defaults: Use default values if configuration not found Type safety: ConfigDB is type-safe (uses template parameter) Configuration setting and getting Hierarchical configuration lookup
5. ConfigDB (7/7). Configuration object usage
6. Factory Pattern (1/6). Factory Pattern Basics Factory registration Factory creation Type override Instance override
6. Factory Pattern (2/6). Factory Creation: Using type_id::create() Type Override: Substituting base class with extended class Instance Override: Overriding specific instances Purpose: Automatically register class with factory Usage: Must be inside class definition
6. Factory Pattern (3/6). Purpose: Create objects/components via factory Syntax: ClassName::type_id::create(name, parent) Key: Factory applies overrides automatically Purpose: Replace all instances of base class with extended class Usage: Set in test's build_phase() before creating components
6. Factory Pattern (4/6). Purpose: Replace specific instance with extended class Usage: Set in test's build_phase() before creating components Effect: Only specified instance is overridden Purpose: Get type wrapper for override operations Usage: Used in override methods
6. Factory Pattern (5/6). Type override affects all instances Instance override affects specific instances Overrides enable test customization Factory macros (uvm_object_utils, uvm_component_utils) register classes Factory creation (type_id::create()) applies overrides automatically
6. Factory Pattern (6/6). Type override: Affects all instances of the base class Instance override: Affects only the specified instance Factory creation demonstrated Type override demonstrated Instance override demonstrated
7. Objections (1/6). Objection Mechanism Raising objections Dropping objections Phase completion Simulation control
7. Objections (2/6). Dropping Objections: Allow phase completion Multiple Objections: Per-component objection tracking Coordinated Completion: Phase completes when all objections dropped Purpose: Keep phase running until objection is dropped Usage: Call at start of run_phase() or other run-time phases
7. Objections (3/6). this: Component raising objection description: Optional description for named objections Key: Must raise objection if doing work in run-time phase Purpose: Signal that work is complete Usage: Call when work in phase is finished
7. Objections (4/6). Pattern: Raise at start, drop when complete Key: Ensures phase doesn't end prematurely Purpose: Track multiple independent tasks Usage: Use named objections for different tasks Key: Each named objection is tracked separately
7. Objections (5/6). Drop objection when work completes Phase completes when all objections dropped Multiple objections per component supported Raise at start: Call raise_objection() at beginning of work Drop when done: Call drop_objection() when work completes
7. Objections (6/6). Named objections: Use for tracking multiple tasks Must match: Each raise_objection() must have matching drop_objection() Objection raising and dropping Phase completion control Multiple objection handling
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (1/8). Purpose: Register class with UVM factory Location: Inside class definition Enables: Factory creation and overrides Syntax: ClassName::type_id::create(name, parent) Returns: Handle to created object/component
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (2/8). UVM_LOW - Always displayed (default) UVM_MEDIUM - Medium detail (most common) UVM_HIGH - High detail UVM_FULL - Full detail UVM_DEBUG - Debug-level detail
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (3/8). Get configuration in component's build_phase() Always check return value of get() Provide default values if configuration not found Use hierarchical paths for component-specific configuration Must raise objection if doing work in run-time phase
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (4/8). Phase completes when all objections are dropped Each raise_objection() must have matching drop_objection() Purpose: Component identification Usage: Logging, debugging, hierarchical paths Purpose: Generate and send transactions to driver
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (5/8). Flow: Sequence → Sequencer → Driver → DUT Purpose: Post-processing after randomization Usage: Calculate expected results, validate data Purpose: Driver-sequencer communication Methods:
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (6/8). item_done(): Signal transaction processing complete Flow: Sequencer provides → Driver receives → DUT Purpose: Broadcast transactions to subscribers Usage: Monitor sends transactions to scoreboard, coverage, etc. Purpose: Receive transactions from monitor
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (7/8). Purpose: Connect analysis port to analysis export Usage: Establish monitor → scoreboard communication Purpose: Get virtual interface handle Usage: Driver/monitor access DUT signals via virtual interface Setting: uvm_config_db#(virtual interface_type)::set(null, "*", "vif", vif_inst)
8. UVM Functions and Methods Reference (8/8). Parameters: Test class name (string) Behavior: Creates test instance, executes all phases Override: +UVM_TESTNAME=TestName command line option
Run: Example 3.1: Class Hierarchy. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE3.md.
Run: Example 3.2: Phases. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE3.md.
Run: Example 3.3: Reporting. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE3.md.
Run: Example 3.4: ConfigDB. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE3.md.
Run: Example 3.5: Factory. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE3.md.
Run: Example 3.6: Objections. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository. Execute from course root or example directory — see docs/MODULE3.md.
Next section: Hands-on examples.
Module 3 self-check. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Exercise scaffold. Review the code on screen and match it to files in the repository.
Example 1: Class Hierarchy. Transaction Class (MyTransaction): Extends uvm_sequence_item (uvm_object hierarchy) Driver Class (MyDriver): Extends uvm_driver (uvm_component hierarchy) Monitor Class (MyMonitor): Extends uvm_monitor (uvm_component hierarchy) Agent Class (MyAgent): Extends uvm_agent, demonstrates component composition Environment Class (MyEnv): Extends uvm_env, top-level...
Demo: Class Hierarchy. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 2: Phases. Build-Time Phases: Top-down execution (parent before child) Run-Time Phases: Bottom-up execution (child before parent) Cleanup Phases: Bottom-up execution (child before parent) Phase Execution Order: Demonstrates all UVM phases module3/examples/phases/README.md
Demo: Phases. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 3: Reporting. Severity Levels: INFO, WARNING, ERROR, FATAL Verbosity Levels: UVM_LOW, UVM_MEDIUM, UVM_HIGH, UVM_FULL, UVM_DEBUG Message Formatting: Formatted messages with data values Hierarchical Reporting: Component context in messages module3/examples/reporting/README.md
Demo: Reporting. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 4: ConfigDB. Setting Configuration: Global and component-specific Getting Configuration: Hierarchical lookup Configuration Objects: Complex configuration data Scalar Values: Simple configuration values module3/examples/configdb/README.md
Demo: ConfigDB. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 5: Factory. Factory Registration: Automatic registration via uvm_object_utils Factory Creation: Using type_id::create() Type Override: Substituting base class with extended class Instance Override: Overriding specific instances module3/examples/factory/README.md
Demo: Factory. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Example 6: Objections. Raising Objections: Keep simulation running Dropping Objections: Allow phase completion Multiple Objections: Per-component objection tracking Coordinated Completion: Phase completes when all objections dropped module3/examples/objections/README.md
Demo: Objections. Watch the terminal output and confirm you see the expected pass message.
Next section: Common pitfalls.
Class Hierarchy. Create transaction classes extending uvm_sequence_item Create component classes extending uvm_component Build component hierarchy Test component creation
Phases. Implement all build-time phases Implement run-time phases Implement cleanup phases Verify phase execution order
Reporting. Use different severity levels Control verbosity Format messages with data Test hierarchical reporting
ConfigDB. Set global configuration Set component-specific configuration Get configuration in components Use configuration objects
Factory. Register classes with factory Create objects using factory Implement type overrides Implement instance overrides
Objections. Raise objections in run_phase Drop objections when work completes Test multiple objections Verify phase completion
Next section: Practice & assessment.
By now you should be able to explain the following. Understand UVM class hierarchy (uvm_object vs uvm_component) Master UVM phases (build-time, run-time, cleanup) Use UVM reporting effectively (severity, verbosity, formatting) Configure components using ConfigDB Understand factory pattern (registration, creation, overrides) From MODULE3 Learning Outcomes.
By now you should be able to explain the following. Structure UVM testbenches properly From MODULE3 Learning Outcomes.
Exercises. Class Hierarchy Phases Reporting ConfigDB Factory
Exercises. Objections
Assessment checklist. Understands UVM class hierarchy Masters UVM phases Uses UVM reporting effectively Configures components using ConfigDB Understands factory pattern
In summary: Master UVM class hierarchy and phases Next up: Next module in course. Master UVM class hierarchy and phases Complete module3/CHECKLIST.md Review module3/EXAMPLES.md and run each lab Next: Next module in course